A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives
- Supreme Court of the United States 1968-1994 (bulk 1972-1987)
  - Subject Files 1972-1987
    - General
      - Address Lists
        - Family Service Association of America, 1980 (Box 133)
        - Federal Judicial Conference, 1971-1978 (Box 133)
        - Forum Club, 1971-1981 (Box 133)
        - Hollins College - Omnibus Club, 1967-1978 (Box 133)
        - Philip Morris, 1966-1972 (Box 133)
        - Photographic - Sperry & Hutchinson,, 1959-1971 (Box 133)
        - Supreme Court, 1970-1978 (Box 133)
        - U.S. Army Special Branch Graduates, 1976 & n.d. (Box 133)
        - Virginia Bar Association - Virginia Commission On Constitutional Revision, 1968-1978 (Box 133)
        - Washington and Lee University, 1960, 1971-1979 (Box 133)
      - Alibi Club, 1975-1986 (Box 133)
      - Allen, Ed, re Duck Hunting, 1976-1980 (Box 133)
      - Alsop, Mrs. Benjamin P., Jr., 1974-1975 (Box 133)
      - American Bar Association, 1971-1987 (Box 133)
      - American Bar Foundation, 1971-1975 (Box 133)
      - American College of Trial Lawyers, 1973-1979 (Box 133)
      - Biographical, 1982-1987 (Box 133)
      - Chamber of Commerce, 1971-1975 (Box 133)
        This file deals with Jack Anderson's column about Powell's Attack On American Free Enterprise memorandum.
      - Combined Federal Campaign, 1974-1975 (Box 134)
      - Cosmos Club, 1972 (Box 134)
      - Danzig, Richard, 1979 (Box 134)
        The subject of this file is the choice of Director of the Selective Service System.
      - Devitt Award Committee, 1983-1988 (Box 134)
      - Lord de la Warr Visit, 1980 (Box 134)
      - Electronic Surveillance, 1967-1972 (Box 134)
        Printed materials are at the end of this file.
      - Eppard v. Wilkerson, 1972 (Box 134)
      - Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, 1972-1981 (Box 135)
      - Freedom of Information Act, 1979 (Box 135)
      - Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, 1972-1981 (Box 135)
      - German (Richmond, Virginia), 1978-1982 (Box 135)
      - Howard, A.E. Dick, 1974-1977 (Box 135)
        Concerns Howard's Woodrow Wilson Fellowship.
      - Hunton & Williams History, 1974-1985 (Box 135)
      - Hunton & Williams - Storage of Files, 1971-1972 (Box 135)
      - Hutcherson, Lillian 1972 (Box 135)
      - Library of Congress - Disposition of Personal Papers, 1975-1976, 1982 (Box 135)
      - London Visit, 1973 (Box 135)
      - Media Criticism
        - Introductory Memorandum, June 29, 1981 (Box 135)
        - Introductory Memorandum, June 29, 1981 (Box 135)
        - General Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 135)
        - Fred Graham Broadcast, 1981 (Box 135)
        - Memoranda and Working Papers, 1979-1981 (Box 135)
        - Research Materials, n.d. (Box 135)
        - Clippings, 1980-1985 (Box 135)
      - National Defense, 1977-1981 (Box 135)
      - Oral History
        - Interview with Olavi Maru, 1975 (Box 135)
        - Interview with Robert Pratt, 1975-1986 (Box 135)
        - Edward R. Murrow Biography, 1984 (Box 135)
      - University of Pennsylvania Moot Court, 1977 (Box 135)
      - Powhatan Hunt Club, 1978 (Box 136)
      - Richmond Chambers - Summer Recesses, 1972-1985 (Box 136)
      - Robson, David, 1978 (Box 136)
      - Senate Youth Program, Hearst Foundation, 1983-1984 (Box 136)
      - Sloan Fellows, 1981-1982 (Box 136)
      - Story File, 1956-1977 & n.d. (Box 136)
        Humorous stories collected for inclusion in speeches.
      - Taylor, Maxwell
        - Book Chapter Typescript, c. 1987 (Box 136)
        - Foreword to Book, 1987 (Box 136)
        - Clippings, 1982-1987 (Box 136)
        - Correspondence, 1974-1985 (Box 136)
      - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, 1976-1979 (Box 136)
      - Virginia State Bar Association, 1977, 1983 (Box 136)
      - Wilkinson (J. Harvie III) Nomination for Fourth Circuit Judgeship
        - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 136)
        - Clippings, 1983-1984 (Box 136)
      - Woodward Book ( The Brethren)
        - Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 136)
        - Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 136)
    - Supreme Court Business (Box 137-141)
      This subseries contains subject files about day-to-day Court administration and operation. Included here is almost a foot of files on Powell's service on the Court's budget committee. There is an equal amount of documentation concerning disqualification problems. These files deal with actual and potential conflicts of interest concerning cases that Powell might have heard as a member of the Supreme Court. The conflicts primarily involved Hunton & Williams retained clients, and companies in which Powell had investments.
      A third portion of this subseries is approximately a foot of material related to the Ethics in Government Act of 1978, which required detailed financial disclosure by federal judges. The resolution of conflicts between compliance with the Disqualification Act of 1974 and this newer law is documented here.
      The "Word Processing Committee" files, along with the related "Linda Blandford" file, reveal the role of Justice Powell in automating the drafting and printing of opinions within the court. Powell saw to it that Ms. Blandford, a secretary in his chambers, was recognized and compensated for her role in the development of Atex, the Court's first automated information system.
      There is extensive documentation of Powell's service on the committee that reviewed Supreme Court rules, and the commission that examined the workload of the National Court of Appeals system. Correspondence with Supreme Court officers such as the Chief Deputy Clerk, the Marshal's Office and the Social Secretary of the Court are also found here.
      Though Justice Powell refrained from making public or private statements about Court opinions, there is a file present entitled "Correspondence as to Court Opinions." Powell's side of the correspondence is primarily to say that Justices generally do not comment on cases. See see the correspondence at 10.2.1 with such trusted friends as Colgate Darden, Paul Freund, Gerald Gunther and Anthony Lewis for substantive discussions of cases.
      - Blandford, Linda A., 1976-1981 (Box 137)
      - Bicentennial of the Constitution, 1986 (Box 137)
      - Budget, 1977-1987 (Box 137)
      - Capital Cases, 1984 (Box 138)
      - Cases for Special Study and Summer Reading, 1972-1975 (Box 138)
      - Chambers, New, 1972 (Box 138)
      - Chief Deputy Clerk (Hiring of), 1980 (Box 138)
      - Civil Rights of Institutionalized Persons, 1981 (Box 138)
      - Correspondence with Clerk of the Court, 1972-1987 (Box 138)
      - Court Cars, Use of, 1986-1987 (Box 138)
      - Court Procedure, 1981 (Box 138)
      - Discovery (Federal Rules of Civil Procedure), 1976-1983 (Box 138)
      - Disqualifications
        - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1969-1987 (Box 138)
        - Memoranda
          - General, 1971-1982 (Box 138)
          - Clerks, 1976-1987 (Box 138)
        - Printed Material, 1970-1973 (Box 138)
      - Ethics In Government Act, 1977-1987 (Box 139)
      - Extra Judicial Income, 1972-1977 (Box 140)
      - Galloway, Gail, 1973-1976 (Box 140)
      - Inauguration, Presidential, 1981 (Box 140)
      - Legal Officers, 1977-1981 (Box 140)
      - Marshall's Office, 1972-1987 (Box 140)
      - Parking, 1972-1982 (Box 140)
      - Oaths of Office, 1976-1977 & n.d. (Box 140)
      - Opinions, Correspondence re, 1973-1978 (Box 140)
      - Opinion Indices, 1976 & 1987 (Box 140)
      - Opinion Lists by Term, 1971-1986 (Box 140)
      - Portrait-George Augusta, 1982, 1985-1986 (Box 140)
      - Shelton, Peggy, 1972 (Box 140)
      - Sloan v. Nixon, 1973 (Box 140)
      - Social Secretary, 1972-1981 (Box 140)
      - Supreme Court Rules, 1977-1986 (Box 140)
      - Taylor & Daly v. American Bar Association, 1974 (Box 141)
      - Threats, 1980 (Box 141)
      - Word Processing Committee, 1980-1986 (Box 141)
      - Workload of the Court
        - Correspondence, 1972-1983 (Box 141)
        - Speeches and Research Materials, 1972-1984 (Box 141)
    - Supreme Court Entertaining (Box 141)
      The mutual bond between Justice Powell and his clerks, was maintained through the annual clerks' reunion. These reunions included a dinner in the Supreme Court Building and brunch at the Alibi Club. The plans for these occasions dominate this subseries. There are also papers relating to the several dinners that Jo and Lewis Powell hosted at the Supreme Court Building for the other Justices and their spouses.
      - General 1976-1986 (Box 141)
      - Clerks' Reunion 1976-1996 (Box 141)
  - Opinion Assignments 1972-1987 (Box 141A)
    Records of case assignments to Justices, and, in turn, to clerks within the Powell chambers.
  - Supreme Court Cases 1972-1987
    - Case Files 1972-1987 (Box 146-286)
      The series Case Files include most of the cases in which writs of certiorari were granted(i.e., cases the court agreed to hear) during Powell's fifteen and one half years on the court. Cases not documented are those from which Powell recused himself or those in which he did not participate because of absence from the court due to illness. In all, there are approximately 2500 cases (140 cu.ft.) here. Powell wrote in some 500 opinions. In about half of these cases, Powell wrote the majority opinion. The remainder were concurring and dissenting opinions.
      It is important to note that most cases in which writs of certiorari were denied or which were disposed of by per curium order are most often not documented here except as they are mentioned in the "order lists" discussed below. Records of these cases were destroyed in routine records maintenance by order of Justice Powell.
      The files are arranged by Supreme Court terms. Note, however, that cases are often granted certiorari during one term, but decided in the next term. (Thus case 82-206 is found in October Term 1983 -- the term during the decision in the case was announced.) Additionally special application cases -- often involving stays of execution -- are found in each term. Cases for which the Supreme Court has original jurisdiction - - cases which come directly to the Court without having been heard in a lower court -- are also included.
      The documentation for each case varies from one thin folder to almost 2 feet of materials for the Bakke case. Forms of materials include: "pool" memoranda, docket sheets noting certiorari votes; bench memoranda prepared by clerks; bench notes from the hearing of oral arguments; notes from the Justices' private conferences; inter-chamber correspondence; drafts of opinions; printing of draft opinions; and printed "slip" opinions. News clippings were sometimes added to the files by Powell chambers staff.
      The files are arranged by Supreme Court terms which begin each October and typically end in June (e.g., a decision announced at the end of October Term 1975 would be rendered in May or June 1976). Within each term, the cases are arranged by Supreme Court docket number.
    - Ancillary Case File Materials
      - General Correspondence and Memoranda, 1972-1973 & 1981 (Box 286A)
        These files are all anomalies. There is one file each on: cases for possible reargument; correspondence and a memorandum re cases denied certiorari or decided per curium; certiorari memos for denied cases; correspondence and memoranda about a number of obscenity cases; and memoranda and notes from a September 28, 1981 conference on three Georgia capital cases.
      - Memoranda Re Stay Applications, 1972-1981 (Box 286B-286C)
        These memoranda were prepared for Justice Powell by his clerks or other Supreme Court clerks. The clerks briefed Powell on the facts and merits of the applications and made recommendations for action.
      - Order Lists, 1972-1986 (Box 286D-286G)
        These files contain listings of cases considered for certiorari or appeal, and applications for admission to the Supreme Court Bar. Brief summaries of actions are often included. Copies of the Court's printed certiorari decisions with comments and dissents are also found in these files.
      - Annotated Slip Opinions, 1973-1990 (Box 286H)
        These are some forty five Supreme Court slip opinions that Justice Powell annotated as he read or re-read them. Nine of these are from after Powell retired from the Court.
      - Card Index to Case Files, 1972-1987 (Box 286I-286M)
        This card index, keyed to the names in case titles, was created by Powell secretary Sally Smith. It is a cumulative index and is arranged alphabetically.
  - Speeches, Writings, and Interviews 1972-1987 (Box 287-302)
    The series Speeches, Writings and Interviews, 16 cu. ft., includes the subseries: "Bound Speeches, 1971-1989," "Speech Files, 1972-1987," and "Speech Materials". The "Speech Materials" are memoranda, clippings and other printed materials arranged by subject. These were used for speech ideas and factual documentation.
    The "Speech Files" include: drafts and reading copies of Powell speeches; research materials used in preparing an address; correspondence preceding and following the speech; and records concerning lodging and travel.
    - Bound, 1971-1989 (Box 288)
      There are three volumes divided by years as follows: 1971-1977; 1977-1984; & 1985-1989. The last volume contains several years of Powell's retirement from the Court. Each volume has a table of contents. Volume one includes an introduction by Powell. All but a handful of the bound speeches are duplicated in the Speech Files section below. The Speech Files, by contrast, contain many speeches not included in the bound volumes.
    - Speech Files 1972-1987
      - Brigham Young University, April 13, 1972 (Box 289)
      - An Overburdened Supreme Court, June 30, 1972 (Box 289)
        Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, The Greenbriar, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia.
      - Virginia State Bar Association, July 14, 1972 (Box 289)
        The Greenbriar, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia.
      - Virginia Bar Association Memorial, July 17, 1972 (Box 289)
        Honoring John Stewart Battle. Delivered at The Greenbriar, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia.
      - Summary of Impressions of First Term on Court, August 8, 1972 (Box 289)
        American College of Trial Lawyers Banquet, San Francisco, California.
      - American Bar Association Prayer Breakfast, August 13, 1972 (Box 289)
        San Francisco, California.
      - Washington and Lee University Alumni Dinner, September 29, 1972 (Box 289)
        New York, New York.
      - Swearing-In of Richard H. Poff, August 30, 1972 (Box 289)
        Virginia Supreme Court, Richmond, Virginia.
      - University of Virginia Law Review Banquet, March 3, 1973 (Box 289)
        Charlottesville, Virginia.
      - Antioch School of Law, March 31, 1973 (Box 289)
        Washington, D.C.
      - Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, April 11, 1973 (Box 289)
        El Paso, Texas
      - Introduction of Virginius Dabney, June 29, 1973 (Box 289)
        Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, Hot Springs, Virginia
      - Richmond Rotary Club, July 17, 1973 (Box 289)
      - Washington and Lee University Founders Day, January 21, 1974 (Box 289)
        Lexington, Virginia.
      - The Role of Legal Education in the Community, March 13, 1974 (Box 289)
        T.C. Williams School of Law, Bar Association of Richmond, Virginia.
      - Clinical Education In Law School, May 4, 1974 (Box 289)
        Dedication of the University of South Carolina Law School Building, Columbia, South Carolina.
      - Retirement of Dean Page Keeton, May 6, 1974 (Box 289)
        University of Texas School of Law, Austin, Texas.
      - The Level of Supreme Court Advocacy, May 27, 1974 (Box 289)
        Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, New Orleans, Louisiana
      - Washington and Lee University, July 19, 1974 (Box 289)
      - Retirement of Chief Justice Harold F. Snead, September 6, 1974 (Box 289)
      - Tribute to Chief Justice Earl Warren, November 20, 1974 (Box 289)
      - Dedication to Ross L. Malone, 1975 (Box 289)
        Washington and Lee Law Review Volume XXXII, Number 1, Winter 1975.
      - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary of the College Chancellor Emil Gumpert, Founder of the ACTL, March 10, 1975 (Box 289)
        American College of Trial Lawyers Banquet, Acapulco, Mexico.
      - The Supreme Court - How It Operates, April 1, 1975 (Box 289)
        Northwestern School of Law, Portland, Oregon.
      - Appellate Advocacy: The Problem and the Need, April 29, 1975 (Box 289)
        Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, Orlando, Florida.
      - Selected Cases Decided 1974 Term, June 26, 1975 (Box 290)
        Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, The Homestead, Warm Springs, Virginia.
      - Award For Courageous Advocacy to Barnabas F. Sears, July 31, 1975 (Box 290)
        American College of Trial Lawyers, Montreal, Canada.
      - Myths and Misconceptions, August 11, 1975 (Box 290)
        American Bar Association, Montreal, Canada.
      - Brigham Young Law School Building Dedication, September 5, 1975 (Box 290)
        Provo, Utah.
      - Memorial to Orison S. Marden, October 29, 1975 (Box 290)
        The Association of the Bar of the City of New York.
      - Dudley Sharp, November 15, 1975 (Box 290)
        Colonial Williamsburg.
      - Supreme Court Justices From Virginia, January 26, 1976 (Box 290)
        Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Commemorative Session of the General Assembly, January 31, 1976 (Box 290)
      - Introduction of Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, February 7, 1976 (Box 290)
        College of William and Mary Alumni Association, Virginia Beach, Virginia.
      - Preface to Biography by Eugene C. Gerhart, February 21, 1976 (Box 290)
        Biography of Arthur D. Vanderbilt.
      - Introduction to Virginia Bar Association Educational Television Program, April 3, 1976 (Box 290)
        Supreme Court Building, Washington, DC
      - Inauguration of the Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law at Yeshiva University, April 11, 1976 (Box 290)
        Powell received honorary Doctor of Laws degree. The New York Hilton, New York City.
      - American Dermatological Association, May 8, 1976 (Box 290)
        Williamsburg, Virginia.
      - Report To the Fifth Circuit, May 24, 1976 (Box 290)
        fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, Houston, Texas.
      - Virginia Declaration of Rights Commemoration, June 12, 1976 (Box 291)
        Colonial Williamsburg, Virginia.
      - Report to the Fifth Circuit, June 28, 1976 (Box 291)
        Houston, Texas.
      - Citizenship Ceremony, July 5, 1976 (Box 291)
      - The Legal Profession: Organization, Discipline and Professional Responsibility, August 10, 1976 (Box 291)
        Powell chaired this program at the American Bar Association Meeting, Atlanta, Georgia.
      - Legal Services Revisited, August 10, 1976 (Box 291)
        Program during annual meeting of the American Bar Association, Atlanta, Georgia.
      - Report On the Court, August 11, 1976 (Box 291)
        Labor Law Section, American Bar Association annual meeting, Atlanta, Georgia.
      - Acceptance of Honorary Membership in American College of Trial Lawyers on Behalf of Thurgood Marshall, August 7, 1976 (Box 291)
        Atlanta, Georgia.
      - Richmond Chamber of Commerce, September 23, 1976 (Box 291)
      - Fiftieth Anniversary Dinner, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, November 12, 1976 (Box 291)
      - Retirement of J. Harvie Wilkinson, Jr. As Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Trustee, November 13, 1976 (Box 291)
      - Dedication of John Marshall Courts Building, January 30, 1977 (Box 291)
      - Reforms of the Federal Judicial System April 27, 1977 (Box 291)
        Presentation of the Learned Hand Medal to Justice Powell. Federal Bar Council, New York, New York.
      - Bork Committee, May 2, 1977 (Box 291)
        Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, Birmingham, Alabama.
      - Dedication of Lewis Hall, Washington and Lee University, May 7, 1977 (Box 291)
      - Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, June 24, 1977 (Box 291)
        The Homestead, Hot Springs, Virginia.
      - Access To Federal Courts, July 8-10, 1977 (Box 291)
        Utah and Idaho Bar Meeting, Sun Valley, Idaho.
      - American Bar Association Meeting, August 5-10, 1977 (Box 291)
        Chicago, Illinois.
      - Richmond Academy of Medicine, September 13, 1977 (Box 291)
      - Introduction of the Chief Justice, October 22, 1977 (Box 291)
        John Marshall House, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Party Honoring William Clements October 26, 1977 (Box 291)
        F Street Club, Washington, DC.
      - Retirement as Historic Williamsburg Foundation Trustee, October 12, 1977 (Box 291)
      - Princeton University, October 18, 1977 (Box 291)
        Princeton, New Jersey.
      - Ethyl Corporation Anniversary Dinner, November 30, 1977 (Box 291)
        Commemorating the fifteenth anniversary the acquisition of Ethyl Corporation by Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Company. New York, New York.
      - International Freedom Prize Dinner, January 24, 1978 (Box 291)
      - The Lawyer As a Citizen February 25, 1978 (Box 291)
        University of Virginia Law Review Banquet, Charlottesville, Virginia.
      - Supreme Court In Action: United States v. Chadwick and Searches Incident to Lawful Arrests May 2, 1978 (Box 292)
      - American Bar Association Meeting, August 4-10, 1978 (Box 292)
        Includes Prayer Breakfast remarks, receipt of an honorary degree from Columbia University at a convocation in celebration of the centenary of the American Bar Association and a session considering the elimination of oral argument from appellate courts. New York, New York.
      - Reforms - Long Overdue October 18, 1978 (Box 292)
        Orison S. Marden Lecture, Association of the Bar of the City of New York.
      - Phi Kappa Sigma Dinner, October 20, 1978 (Box 292)
      - Rule of Law - A common Heritage, October 21, 1978 (Box 292)
        English Speaking Union, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Justice Potter Stewart December 1978 (Box 292)
        Foreword to Hofstra Law Review.
      - Charter Day Address, College of William and Mary, February 10, 1979 (Box 293)
      - Harry A. Blackmun, Honorary Fellowship in the American College of Trial Lawyers, March 12, 1979 (Box 293)
        Boca Raton, Florida.
      - Constitutional Interpretation; Interview - Kenyon College, May 27, 1979 (Box 293)
        Powell was at Kenyon to receive an honorary degree. Gambier, Ohio.
      - Notes for Fourth Circuit Speech, June 28-30, 1979 (Box 293)
      - Introduction of Amalya L. Kearse, August 11, 1979 (Box 293)
        American College of Trial Lawyers, Dallas, Texas.
      - American Bar Association Meeting, August 13-15, 1979 (Box 293)
        Includes papers re session
      - 200th Anniversary of the Supreme Court of Virginia, August 30, 1979 (Box 293)
      - Griffin B. Bell, September 7, 1979 (Box 293)
        Atlanta Bar Association, Atlanta, Georgia.
      - Introduction of Justice John Paul Stevens, January 24, 1980 (Box 294)
      - Induction of David Shannon as President of Virginia Union University, March 7, 1980 (Box 294)
      - What Really Goes On At the Court May 1, 1980 (Box 294)
        Southwestern Legal Foundation, Dallas, Texas.
      - Remarks - Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, May 19, 1980 (Box 294)
        Dallas, Texas.
      - Decisions of Interest by Our Court June 27, 1980 (Box 294)
        Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, The Greenbrier, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia.
      - The Role of the Supreme Court July 1980 (Box 295)
        Salzburg, Austria.
      - War/Peace Issue October 2, 1980 (Box 295)
        Memorandum prepared for unknown purpose.